Hey guys um welcome back. So now we are
going to talk about distributed
execution in Tuska. How we can set this
up and how we can get it running. So
basically triggering test events from
our tuska commander and then they get uh
executed on different agents. Okay. So
this is the architecture of uh the decks
with AOS. And now AOS stands for
automation object service. And you can
see here on the Tuska server which we
have already set up the AOS and the
distribution uh service are already
running. Okay. So the AOS uh has its own
workspace and they act as the middleman
between your TSA commander and the
distribution agents. Okay. So whenever
uh we trigger any test events from our
workspace in TSA commander it gets
executed or it triggers the execution
from the server and the server then
distributes it to different agents.
Okay. So once this agents finish their
execution they will return the results
back to server and the server will then
communicate with the automation object
service workspace uh which will again uh
save the results back to the common
repository which is the database. It can
also retrieve any test data which is
required from the workspace uh from TSA
commander and then it can pass it on to
the distribution server. Okay, which
will be used for uh executing your test
events. So this is how
uh the whole flow of uh the distributed
execution works in TSA and this is the
whole architecture. Okay. So one part of
it uh we have already done which is the
Tska server. Now our automation object
service and the distribution service are
already running. Now we have to set up
these uh agents. Okay. And we have to
also set up this workspace also. We have
to do some configurations so that uh
this whole setup can be replicated and
uh we we can start executing our test
events uh on
different distribution or which are
known as text agents.
Okay. So this is what uh we are going to
do now. And the there are many parts to
it. So I'll be taking it slowly uh each
part right. So first we are going to set
up a AOS workspace. This should be set
up on the TSCA server. So wherever you
have installed Tska server you have to
create a separate workspace that will be
the automation object service workspace
and uh you should not use it for your
regular day-to-day work. You should
always use the workspace which you have
set up uh on the common repository uh on
which are being used by the Tska
commander. This will be used by the
automation object service and it should
not be opened or u used for any other
purpose. Okay. Otherwise your text will
stop working. So yeah so we will first
set up this uh TSA workspace. Um then we
will uh do some configurations. Uh we'll
create test events. Okay. Um and we will
create different configurations. Uh
we'll set up an agent. We'll connect it
to our uh workspace. Okay. And uh it
will also be connected to the TUSCa
server or the DEX server and then we'll
trigger the events and it should be
executed on that particular agent. Okay.
Now all of this I'm going to do again on
my own machine uh because of lack of
servers but you can always go ahead and
set it up on different Windows servers
as I explained you earlier or different
machines even
okay right um so let's go ahead and open
our Oscar commander now I'm going to use
the multi-user workspace uh which is the
multi-demo so let's open this
Okay, actually uh we had to create a
workspace. So I don't even need to open
this. Uh but anyways, I will close this.
So this is the workspace which we had
created earlier. It is the multi-user
workspace. Uh so one thing to note uh
very important is for uh distributed
execution. It will only work with
multi-user workspaces. Okay. So you have
to create a workspace multi-user
workspace on a particular repository
which could be any database. Okay. So
that's uh very
important. So I'll cancel this. Uh we
are going to create a new uh workspace
now. So let's click on create
new.
Okay. Just a minute. Yeah. Um and then
I'm going to use uh SQLite for now.
Obviously it's not recommended for
production environments. You have to use
Oracle or SQL server or DB2. Okay. So
I'll be using the existing repository uh
which I have created already because uh
it should be the same repository where
you have created your multi-user
workspace. Okay. So that's also
important. Don't create a new repository
again.
uh they both should be connected to the
same repository as we have seen um in
this particular diagram you can see this
is the common repository and both are
connected to this
okay so branch will be master um and I
will create the new workspace in this
particular path I will going to create
um I or I will give a name here
something like multi- aos
Okay. Um, and then you should not be
creating a slim workspace for AOS. It
doesn't work. So don't select
this. And let's go ahead and create this
workspace. So this is the workspace
which is specifically made for AOS.
Okay.
And depending on how large your
repository is or it will take very
little time or very uh very uh huge time
if your workspace or your repository
size is too big. Okay, because it has to
update all the objects um before it
creates a new workspace.
So it may take more time or it may take
very less time like me because my
repository is almost a very it's a very
little size of for my repository. I
don't have many tests or anything.
Okay. So let's log into this.
Uh we will just verify this workspace
and then uh we are going to close this
because as I said earlier uh you should
not be using this workspace. Okay. it
will be used by the uh AOS
service and
let's just verify here the project name
is correct multi-demo okay and uh we
have got the same repository because we
can see some of the similar objects
which are present in my other workspace
okay
so this part is done now uh we have
created our AOS workspace now we can
close this.
Okay. Now, uh the next part is to
uh configure some AOS workspace related
things on the server. Okay. And for
that I'm going to also open my
multi-demo uh workspace or
project and let's go to our server now.
Okay. So on the server uh you need to go
to
settings and here you need to go to
automation object service. Okay.
Although it is in the running state we
need to add a workspace here. So the
workspace which we have created we have
to add it here. Okay. So click on add
new and uh you need to uh provide a name
project root name for this workspace
name username and password. Okay. Now
you can create a maximum of 10 different
workspaces which can work all in pal.
Okay. So if you've got different
projects you want to create different
aos workspaces for that you can do that.
So you can create a maximum of 10 um
right from here. So just click on add
new and then add the details here.
Okay. So um our project root name is
multi. So let's check our project root
name first. Okay. Um I should not have
closed that but let's open this again so
that we can just uh note down these all
these different settings which we need
to provide for our AOS
workspace. Okay. So let me go here.
Workspace name I know it's
multi- aos right and our username is
admin password is
admin I just need to provide the root
name
okay so let me log
here. And as you can see, so our project
root name is multi-demo, but our
workspace name is
still
multi-aos.
Okay. So, uh the project name will
remain same because we are using the
same repository. So, it is multi-demo.
But our workspace name is you can see on
the top it's multiAOS.
Okay. So let's put multi- demo
here. Right. So now go ahead and save
this. Okay. So these are all the changes
we need to do. You can see once I click
on save it will restart all the services
which are related to this.
Okay. So once it restarts it will apply
all these uh settings on that particular
service before uh starting
it. Okay. Um also it's recommended once
this is all set up you can also go ahead
and restart the dex server because the
dex server is connected to this aos. So
it's better uh we restart the deck
server from our services.
Okay. So let's go to
services and let's go to tentis services
and we'll search for the distributed
execution
service. Okay. And we'll restart it once
this uh finishes
off. Okay. So ideally this should also
restart the deck server. But just in
case it doesn't restart uh you should
restart it
manually. Okay. So this is now uh
restarted and it should be running. I
can also restart the monitor because it
is
connected.
Okay. Right. Um, so it is in running
state and if I go back to my
dashboard, refresh it and then you will
see um everything is running again.
Okay, if I go to my monitor which we
will require later on. Okay, currently
no agents are there but we are going to
set up a agent now.
Okay, so the work for this is now
finally done. So we can close this
multios workspace and we can open our
project which is
multi-demo. And here we will be setting
up our dex events uh dex agents. Right.
So the next step is to connect a dex
agent. Now ideally this should be again
a different machine where either a TSka
commander or a TSCA execution agent is
running. Okay. But since uh for this
particular demo um I'm going to use the
same machine. I have set up my TSka
server and Tska commander on but ideally
in idle conditions you should not use
it. either use a different machine or a
different server um where you have set
up a TSA commander or a TSCA execution
agent.
Okay. So
um now we need to start the TSA agent uh
wherever you want to set it up and for
that um we need to go to C program
files and go to Tentis Tuska
server distributed execution. So we have
to go to Dex
server. Okay.
And actually not the deck
server. Just a minute. I think I went
the wrong way. So we need to go to Tuska
test suit and here distributed
execution and here you will find the DEX
agent.exe which we need to run.
Okay. So this is the Tska distribution
agent. So whenever you install Tuska
commander this folder will be created
and you can run this text agent on any
machine where Tska commander is
installed. There's also a separate uh
installation provided. Okay. So whenever
you install TSA commander right on any
particular machine
uh let me show
you. You can you can also set it up as a
dedicated right. I cannot show you here
because it's already installed. But uh
whenever you start the installation
right uh it will ask you an option
whether you want to install the full TSA
commander or you want to install
uh a TSA DEX agent. Okay. So you can
either both ways are correct but ideally
you should just uh install the agent
part not the complete TSCA commander as
it is more memory efficient and also it
will take less space for you. Okay. So
if you just want to use it as a
distribution agent then just install the
agent on that particular machine or if
you want to use both commander and agent
together then you can go ahead and
install the commander and this agent
will be available. Okay. So this is the
path uh where you need to go and then uh
double click on this. Okay. Um if we
ideally we should run it as an
administrator.
Okay. And once it's done, right? So you
will see
uh a monitor which is displayed on your
bottom taskbar. Right. You can see that
currently it is white which means it is
not running. If it is green that means
uh it is configured correctly. If it is
yellow that means it is executing. If it
is red then it means that uh it is
something has not been set up correctly.
Okay. Now you can see it is green. So it
has set it up correctly automatically uh
set up this agent for us. But if it is
not then uh we need to configure the
agent. So right click on this and you
will get the option to configure or stop
the agent.
Okay. So let's go to this uh agent
configuration. You can see here
operating system memory, operating
system type, uh IP address and host
name. It is picked up
automatically. But you can always change
this. Okay. So we'll see uh where this
setting lies and uh how we can change
this. Uh we don't need to set up the
workspace here. Okay? Because uh this is
a a workspace. So we don't need to set
up any workspace for an
agent. Now this is the most important
part connect to server. Uh you can
connect to your text server where it is
set it up. Right? So for me it is local
host. Uh and this is the port
5007. You can always go and verify this
uh on your deck
server. Okay. So go to settings and uh
go to automation object service. Here
you will find the distribution server
address. So you can see it is localhost
5007. Right? So this is uh
the server and the port which you should
give wherever you have set up your TSCA
server or DAX server and this is the
endpoint URL which this agent requires
in order to connect. Okay.
Then um authentication if it requires an
authentication you can do that. So you
can um use RDP okay if this is running
on a particular machine right now it is
running on my local so RDP service is
not available but you can always use
this RDP connection okay so why this is
required uh if you have set this up on a
different machine or server. So if you
enable RDP then it can perform that all
the mouse and keyboard actions on that
particular machine even if it is locked
right uh because if you don't use this
and if the system gets locked then your
test will start failing okay so you have
to give uh choose this RDP connection
and then provide username password the
desktop width height whatever uh is that
for that particular machine
Okay. And then logging. Uh so this will
be the log file. It is present in this
same folder. You can see here this is
the log file. Doska distribution agent.
And ideally it should be set to debug.
So that if any problem comes you can uh
go ahead and debug that particular
problem in your log file. Okay. So go
ahead and click
this. And as you can see green that
means our dex agent is set up correctly.
If you see it is red then that means
something is wrong and you should check
uh or configure that particular agent.
Okay. Now you will see uh if we go back
to our dex
monitor right
so on the agent you can see on the agent
view one agent has popped up now. Okay.
So currently it is in the sleeping state
or idle state. So this is the idle
state. Okay. So this means it is
running. This means it is paused or this
means this means it is stopped. Uh this
means some error has happened. Okay. I
can restart my agent from here. I can do
uh the configuration right from here.
You can see the machine configuration
here. The workspace um the RTP
connection the login. Okay. So this
things we can configure here. For the
endpoint URL, you have to go to the
agent and configure it there. Okay. So
this is all you can do from the agent
view or the
monitor. Okay. So the dex monitor it
will show all the agents which you have
configured right here. So if there are
if they are in running state then they
will be displayed here. If they are not
then uh they won't be available here.
Okay. So what this means is now we have
got one agent which is the text agent
where we can trigger our test events.
Okay. And that will be done through
distributed execution.
Right. So uh this part is now complete.
So we have set up our
oursex agent successfully and it is
available on the monitor. Right now we
need to connect our commander to this
particular agent. Right. So that's the
next step. So let's go back to our
commander. And in commander uh inside
your project when you go inside your
execution right you will see
configurations. So these are the
configurations which are created by
default. Okay. and uh in any
right that means um whichever agent is
available if you use this configuration
uh that particular agent will be
provided the task from the server. Okay.
So whenever we execute any test
event similarly there is RDP where use
RDP is true and supports classic. So in
properties you can see it is true which
means it supports the classic modules
right. So these configurations uh these
three are available by default but we
can add as many as we want. Now what
this means is uh these are the different
configurations which will match the dex
agents. Okay. So uh whatever
configurations you require for your test
to run something like you want to run on
a Chrome browser on a Firefox browser or
on a Edge browser or you want some
specific machine configuration like you
want to run on a specific operating
system like uh you want to run on
Windows 10, 11 or Windows 8, right? Or
or some specific uh RAM size, right? It
depends on what kind of configuration
machine configuration you require and
that machine configuration or any other
configuration can be set up here. Okay.
So we'll see that later. But first let's
go ahead and um execute some test events
now. Right. But before that um what you
can also do is right click on this
configurations and refresh the agents.
Okay. So what it will do it will refresh
the agents but first we need to
configure this or we need to connect our
Tuska commander to the Dex server right
so let's go ahead and do
that so go into uh settings for your
project and here we need to set some
values
okay so in settings under commander and
the distributed execution we need to set
the monitor URL URL.
Okay. And we have already seen this. So
I if you don't know this monitor URL,
you can go back here. And this is the
monitor URL. Localhost 80080 / monitor.
Okay. So copy and paste it
here. And then the server. So here we
need to also give the port. If it is not
the default port, rest of the endpoint
URL will remain same. Distribution
server service manager
service. We just need to change the
server IP address if it is not local
host and the port. Okay. So for me it is
localhost 8080. Uh if you have set it up
on a different server um the port may be
different. It may be 80 and it could be
local host or you can give the IP
address directly here.
Okay. So these two settings you need to
change and then the last one is Tendis
services. So here we need to provide the
server endpoint address. Okay. So
wherever we have set up the server we
need to provide the endpoint address
which is nothing but the local host or
the IP address and with it uh we also
need to give the port. Okay. So local
host and then the port which is
8080. So we need to set up the
distributed execution monitor URL server
and the tri synthesis services. So these
three settings you need to change here
on your commander side. So uh wherever
you are going to trigger any test event
you need to change these settings.
Okay. And uh go ahead and close this. it
will save the settings and let's try and
refresh the agents
now. Okay, once I refresh the agents um
and you can also do uh update
configurations from server if you have
changed anything on the server side. Uh
we'll see
that. Okay. So it is saying
error occur during creation of proper
definition. Check out the project root.
Okay. Yeah, we need to check out the
project root before we update the
configurations. But for now, it's not
required. I will show it when we change
something on the configuration side. But
as you can see now this desktop vision,
right? So which is my uh dex agent host
name, it is now available under any.
Okay. So when you refresh the agents,
all the agents depending on the
configuration how it matches. So all the
agents will be available under any
because it covers all the agents. Okay.
But any specific uh agent configuration
which you have used uh if it matches
this configuration. So if use RDP is
true for my agent then it will appear
here. Right? Similarly if it supports
classic it will appear here. So if I
have a chrome configuration if it
matches that configuration for that
particular dex agent then it will appear
here.
Okay. So, uh this is also important the
number of agents which are running on
the configuration because we are going
to use this configuration inside our
test event.
Okay. So, um you can see test events by
default under any execution folder you
have created. Okay. So, and again as I
said it is not available in single user
workspace. So we might not have seen it
earlier but when we created a multi-user
workspace this test event was created
and this is used for distributed
execution only. Okay. So this test
events will be available here and uh we
can create different test events here.
Okay. What it requires? It requires a
configuration and it requires an
execution list which it can execute.
Okay. So first uh let's go ahead and
check out
this and then I'm going to create a test
event. So this is the test event. Okay.
And let's name it
uh we can give it any name but let's
give it dex
event.
Okay. And um we need to now drag the
configuration. So what configuration you
want to use for this event? I can use
any or I can use any specific
configuration. But let's use any for
now. Okay, because it has got one agent.
You can see here number of agents is
one. So this event will be used in this
agent. If there are 10 agents, the
server will decide which agent is free
and it will distribute it uh on that
particular agent. If you want to run it
on a specific agent then create a
configuration for that and then drag it
uh for your test event and it will be
only executed on that particular
configuration.
Okay. Now this configuration it also
requires an execution list. So I have
created a execution list called text
test.
Okay. Um it contains this uh test uh
test which is very simple test case. uh
it opens the Google URL. Okay. Uh
obviously you can do much more but this
just for this demo purpose I have used.
So I have dragged the test case to here.
I have created execution list. We
already know how to do that. So I'm not
going to repeat it. But u we have to
now drag this execution list into this
configuration.
Okay. So this is the structure of a
distributed execution. you require a
test event, you require a configuration
and you require a execution list. Uh you
can also create a test mandate or
basically any kind of execution uh you
can create and you can drag it down here
so that it is at least
um configured so that it can be run for
this particular event.
Just thinking what else we require but I
think we are now ready to uh execute
this test event on our DEX agent. So
let's go ahead and do
that. You should always check whether
the test agent is in running condition.
You can do it in many ways as I have
shown
you. So we can execute it right from
here. Execute now or we can execute it
now.
Right. Obviously
um if you want to run your test events
right
on a particular server uh at a
particular time you want to trigger them
you can always do that through some CI
client right but we'll see that later.
Um now once you have triggered the test
event okay it should be available on the
event view
right now we can always go to the
details of any particular event
execution like we have done here. Uh
currently you can see the test event
status is cancelled because some error
occurred right and it will show the
details here. So you can see some uh it
failed to retrieve the needed automation
objects right.
So I know by just a socket uh but I
wanted to show you this um how if some
error occurs how it will look and how
you can go back to your details right
but we forgot one thing uh before
executing this test event right so uh
one thing very important thing to note
is whenever you are executing a test
event you have to make sure that all
your test events are checked in or any
particular execution list which is
linked to that test event should be
checked in. Okay. So you can see here
our event is checked out and that is why
it is not able to retrieve that test
object from the workspace. Okay. So
always make sure you check in uh
everything before or at least the test
events which you are running before you
execute the test event. Okay. Otherwise
uh you will have issues like this. So
let's try this again and let's go back
here and execute it
now. Okay. Um so since it is executing
on this particular machine uh we might
see that a new browser will be opened
here and the Google page will appear
right. So that means my execution list
was executed. Okay, because this was a
test case I was running and uh this is
what will happen on your text agent
machine
right and you will see that the event
view that particular test event is now
passed. We have one cancelled, one
passed, right? You can see the start
time, the creator who is if there are
different users. Okay. And the agent
view will be back to uh idle. But while
it is running, you can also monitor the
view and it will be in the execution
state. Okay. So this is how you can
trigger test events and you can run it
on different agents or which are
different remote machines which are
running uh TSCA. Okay. So you can
distribute your uh all the events even
in parallel across this agents. Okay.
Now uh the last part um which is there
is we're talking about configurations
right and where this configuration is
coming from is uh right from you can go
to C program files and go to tric
centiska server and
um I think it is here under deck server
right yeah so if you look under server
deck server you will find configuration
parameters and these are the
configuration parameters which are uh
defined by default. Okay. And you can
see all the different uh operating
systems which are available here and um
the different memory configurations uh
different operating system type. Um and
then there is this additional
configuration which is use RDP and uh
support classic
right and also IP address. Okay. So you
can define all different configurations
right here. Okay. So I can go ahead and
change some configuration like this.
Okay. So here you can see operating
system uh we have got all the different
operating system but we don't have 11.
But I feel I need I want to execute a
particular test on a configuration which
has got Windows 11.
Okay. So I can uh edit any particular
conf configuration. I can also add you
can just copy this uh whole XML uh key
value pairs and you can create your own
configuration. So I can add any as many
configurations I want. I can even add a
test configuration parameter like this
like so I need to put a name uh and then
the parameter values. Okay. So I can
create easily for something like a
chrome or anything. Okay. So now I have
changed this uh windows 11 right here.
So what I need to do if I have changed
something first of all I need to save it
here and uh you need to be in admin mode
to change
this. Okay. So first save it here so
that it is saved on the server and then
uh on the commander we need to uh
retrieve that configuration change right
here. Okay. So for that we need to check
out our root project.
right click on the configurations and
update configurations from the
server. Okay. So now um that will that
particular configuration is applied here
and
u we can even check that uh by creating
a new configuration. So we can create a
new configuration
here. Okay. And here I can create a new
configuration.
So I can name it something like local
right because I'm executing on local
machine so I want something specific for
my local machine. Okay. And once you
create this new configuration you will
see all the properties right. So all the
configuration key values which will
appear on the properties on the right
hand side. So host name, IP address,
memory, use RDP, operating system,
operating system type, memory. So
whatever configurations we had put there
is available here and I can then select
a specific configuration.
Okay. So I can select Windows 11 memory
uh 16 GB operating system
64bit. Now the essence of this is once
you create a new configuration you have
selected some new um configuration key
values for that in the properties right
you have to now match this with your
agent okay so let's go to this configure
agent and here you can see windows 11 16
GB and 64bit right so now this
configuration of the agent is matching
the configuration which I have just
created. Okay. So, let's go ahead and
check in all. And what we'll do, we'll
go and refresh the agents. Now, what is
going to happen is now I'm going to see
a agent pop up on my new configuration
because it matches the properties which
I have defined here with the agent.
Okay. So whenever it matches that
configuration, it is going to put that
agent under that particular
configuration. So that you can just use
this configuration in your test event
and then you can run it on specific
configurations. Right? So you can create
like this different configurations here
based on what you want to execute and
what kind of machine configuration you
require. Right?
So you can do that here and just uh
change the configuration of the agents
which should match with this particular
configuration which you have defined in
configuration parameters doxml right. So
these three things you need to match and
then you need to refresh the agents um
and then it will appear here and you can
use this configuration. Now I can remove
this any here. Okay. So if I check this
out and if I remove this configuration
here and I use my specific configuration
which is local and I can now execute
this event on here. I mean there is no
such change now because it is still
executing on local. I've just got one
agent but you when you have got multiple
agents and you want to run uh your event
on a specific configuration on a
specific agent then this is how uh you
can do this.
Okay. So this was all about distributed
execution. It requires some level of
configuration. So you need to have some
knowledge of uh your whole architecture
um your infrastructure right how where
your TSka server is uh where you have
set up that your IP address port you
have to change a few things like I've
shown you and then um once you are all
set up you can then start executing your
test events or distribute it across
different machines different agents
depending on the configurations you
choose
So there are lots of things to consider
here right but it's very important
distributed execution is one of the most
important things uh or most important
components of TSCA because it provides
you the ability to execute your test uh
events in different machines different
configurations uh even in parallel.
Okay. So this was all about distributed
execution. Uh next we'll be talking
about uh CI/CD how you can trigger this
uh events that is also a TSA CI client.
Uh so we'll look at all of them in the
CI/CD uh session.